The syntactical world is governed by a deductive calculus,
which we can visualize as a theorem-proving computer.
The symbols of this system divide into logical and non-logical.
The axioms divide in the same way. If we only feed in the
so-called logical axioms --which determine the behaviour of the logical symbols-- into our
theorem prover then we are in the world of pure logic.
The outputs of our theorem prover will be logically
valid formulas. We can think of this like the
operating system, operating in the background of mathematics.
Then, to define a mathematical theory, such as group theory, or number
theory, we will fix a set of constants, functions and relations, and
add axioms which determine the behaviour of these new symbols.
The choice of which symbols and axioms to include lead to
different theories. And a theory is just the set of everything
which can be outputted by the theorem proving computer.
So, mathematical truth on the syntactic side is
given by proofs in a deductive calculus.
On the semantic side, truth is given by Tarski's definition: a
sentence is true if and only if it holds in every
model. Let us make this precise — it may feel technical
for a moment, but it leads somewhere interesting.
Formally, a structure — which we denote with the symbol M —
is given by a tuple consisting of a domain, or universe, together
with interpretations of the constants, functions, and relations in the language.
To define the natural numbers with addition and multiplication, for
instance, we need at least the symbols zero, one, the
successor function, addition, multiplication, and the less-than relation.
We interpret zero and one as expected.
The interpretation of functions and relations is a bit more abstract.
For example, the less-than relation is interpreted as the set of
all pairs (a, b) such that a is less than b.
Note that functions are just special relations where
the output is uniquely determined by the inputs.
So the successor function would map to the set of all pair
of numbers such that the second is one greater than the first.
And the addition function is formally the set of all triples
(a, b, c) such that a plus b equals c.
To evaluate a simple equation like one plus two
equals three, we map the constants as expected
and then check whether the resulting
triple belongs to the addition relation.